Okay, I wanted to use another short video
to demonstrate and explain an aspect that
has already occurred for some of you
in your submissions; where you got feedback from
Autotool which said something about eta-reduction.
Yes.
So, something like 'Eta-reduce
the following expression'.
So, what does this mean?
Eta-reduction.
Okay.
It is related to higher order functional
programming, which we'll capture later.
But actually, already at this point, I can
give a few explanations so that you are not so
surprised, maybe, if this
appears in your feedback.
Okay.
So, I will first do this on some example,
which is completely artificial,
and then make a small experiment.
Okay, so what does it mean?
And when, or whether it appears
in situations like the following.
So, let's say you have some function, which
you use in your scene, it takes some arguments,
maybe a color, and maybe it takes some other
picture, an object, the sun, the moon, whatever.
And it also takes a time value, and
it ultimately returns a picture.
Yeah, that's something that
could occur in your submissions.
And maybe it is defined in the
following ways, we have a color,
we get a picture, we get the current time.
And then, well, you have some expressions.
So, let's say we have some additional
function, I don't know what it's called,
that somehow combines and manipulates pictures.
And it's probably not the name that
this function really has, but let's say
that is the definition for this.
And then in this f function that you use to
compose your scene, or to draw part of your scene,
you want to say something like, well, I want
to manipulate and combine, and maybe this
color is passed on to the other function.
And maybe for the picture, you will
actually change it here at this point.
So, maybe what you want to do is that you want
to combine this picture with some other picture,
and a rectangle of these dimensions.
And then you pass this on to the
'manipulateAndCombine' function,
which of course is also, well, it
has some arguments and also has,
of course, a time parameter which, then, it is
used somewhere in the definition, obviously.
Okay.
This is, of course, not a
valid definition here now,
because of all these three places
but let's say it is defined,
and you will pass this on to the other
function, and you also pass the time along.
And this makes perfect sense.
We have three arguments here, the
Color, the Picture, and the Double.
And the function definition has the same
three arguments, the Color, the Picture, and
the Double for the time, and
then it uses our function.
And let's assume that this really has
these parameters so that this works out.
Now, if you had something
like this in your submissions,
then Autotool would suggest
that you should eta-reduce.
And the hint that Autotool would give would
be something like let's throw away these,
let's throw away the "t" argument.
So, what Autotool would say at this point is well,
why don't you define your function like this?
Which might be a bit surprising, since
this "t" has suddenly disappeared.
Yes.
But indeed, if you would actually define
the 'manipulateAndCombine' function and
then wrote your 'f' function like here, like
suggested by Autotool, then it would still work,
despite the fact that here we have the Color,
the Picture and the Double argument, but
the "t" argument doesn't even appear here.
So, we have a three argument function, but we
defined a function only with two arguments.
How can this be?
Well, that is the point of eta-reduction.
Namely, that instead of considering this
"f" as a function of three arguments that
returns a Picture, you could also
consider it as just a function,
which takes two arguments, namely Color
and Picture, and then actually returns
a function from Double to Picture, which is
exactly what this right-hand side here defines.
Yes, we simply don't need to
introduce the time at this point.
If it's not used in this expression, if it's
only passed onward to this other function,
then you might as well say instead of saying
"f" of "c" and "p" and "t" is this function,
this whole expression of "t", you might as well
say "f" of "c" and "p" is just this expression.
Okay.
So, we somehow defer the provision of this time
argument, it makes perfect sense mathematically,
because if it's a function, then it could take
another argument and what would happen with this
additional argument, it would also
be passed on to the other function,
but we don't have to write this because
this is automatic by how functions work.
Okay, so actually, this would also be an accepted
definition and would behave exactly as the other
version and Autotool considers this version,
nicer, more elegant, better style because we
don't introduce this artificial time parameter.
If you're not going to use it at this
point, if you're only going to pass it
on to some other function, we don't
need to introduce it at this point.
Okay.
So, this is somehow the syntactic reason
why this works and how this is interpreted.
And it's also the reason why we, in Haskell,
write arguments with this arrow notation, yes.
If you go back or remember the previous
slide, there was discussion about why
is this not written somehow as: we take three
arguments as it would be in a Java type signature.
Yes, where we would have something like this.
And then here we would also write
it with commas and brackets.
Yes, it would also be a reasonable
way of defining the syntax of Haskell.
But actually, it wouldn't work nicely because
it wouldn't work with eta-reduction, if you
wrote type signatures like this, and if you wrote
function definitions or arguments like this,
then there wouldn't be an immediate syntactic
possibility for omitting this "t" parameter.
Yes, then we would also have
all our brackets here, probably.
And it wouldn't be so easy to say,
well, let's omit the last "t" because
we would expect that "f" always takes
the three arguments in a triple.
Yeah, this wouldn't look so nice or would be
such a nice refactoring to omit one argument.
But with the previous or with the actual
predominant version of type signatures
and function definitions in Haskell, it's a
very simple step to omit this last argument.
Okay, so that's what this means, abstractly.
Let's also look at a concrete and small example.
I copied it from another buffer.
Okay, so it is now really a complete program,
because it also has a meaningful main definition.
Now the question is what will
happen here if I run this now?
Yes, what do I define a
function from Double to Picture?
But again, actually, the function
doesn't take an argument.
Yes, I'd simply say opening
equals and then something.
Why does this make sense?
Well, it does make sense because rectangle
is actually a function of two arguments,
an x and the y coordinate by simply
using it only or providing it only
one argument on the right-hand side here, what
I have created is a function, which is still
awaiting its second argument and
only then will return a Picture.
That is exactly what the type is telling you.
The "opening" is something which awaits
a time, a Double and gives a Picture.
But I don't have to write this down.
I could equivalently write this down, I could
say, well, "opening t" is "rectangle 10 t".
But I don't have to, because this is more
direct and in some sense, more expressive.
What will happen if I run this, and maybe
from this you wouldn't be able to tell.
But if I actually write the explicit argument,
you should know what happens, what will happen
is an animation, we are just increasing time,
one of two dimensions of the rectangle will grow.
Yes, if I run this, I get an
animation of an opening rectangle.
So, it's the y coordinate, because the second
argument here, and the very same thing would have
happened if I had written it in eta reduced form,
simply saying "opening" is "rectangle 10", awaiting
its next argument, which will be the time because
"opening" will be the argument of "animationOf".
So, if I have this eta-reduced version
and run it, it will be the same.
Okay, at this point, one might also wonder where
this is very specific that
it grows in the y direction.
So, if what I wanted the other way around, one
way to get this would be well, then we have
to really introduce the "t" parameter explicitly,
because now we want to know, to express that
the first argument is the time parameter for the
rectangle so that it grows in the x direction.
So, then we would have lost the advantage
of eta-reduction, we would have to introduce
this "t" parameter, but actually Haskell being
a functional language, which has support for
programming on the function level really,
using functions as first-class citizens.
You could actually also express
the same thing by saying: Well,
if you want to have a rectangle, it is
opening in the x direction, then we won’t
and we don't want to explicitly
write down the "t" parameter.
What we really want.
We want to flip the rectangle.
Here, we want to flip the order of the arguments.
So, instead of saying I need to introduce
a "t" parameter, I can still make use of
eta-reduction without
introducing the extra parameter
if I make sure that I change in which
order rectangle takes its arguments.
And this again can be done with a function,
and unsurprisingly, maybe, this
function is called 'flip'.
So, this is a well-defined Haskell program again.
It flips the order of the arguments of the 'rectangle'
function, then it provides one of its arguments,
namely the y coordinate, because of the flipping
here, the y coordinate is now the first one
and the x coordinate, well, it's
still awaiting a time parameter,
which will come when the animation runs.
So, if I run this, I get the
opening rectangle in this direction.
If I omit the "flip", I get the opening
rectangle in the other dimension.
Okay, and all by virtue of eta-reduction,
namely avoiding parameters that are
anyway only passed on to other functions.
It only works if that is the last parameter.
That's why I needed to apply the "flip" in the
case that I want to do the opposite direction.